Guide to the Chemistry Department, Office Files, University of Pittsburgh, 1902-2011 UA.90.08.08
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Chemistry Department, Office Files, University of Pittsburgh
1902-2011
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh
UA.90.08.08
3.125 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The Department of Chemistry at the University of Pittsburgh, begun in 1811, continues to be an influential research institution in the field of chemistry. This collection was created in part through an initiative by the department to collect its history and includes academic, administrative, research-based, and publicity information.
History
The Department of Chemistry at the University of Pittsburgh dates to 1811, when a Dr. Aigster gave lectures in chemistry. Space continued to be provided for chemistry lectures and experimentation until 1864, when $20,000 was raised to support a chemistry, geology, and mineralogy professor. Francis C. Phillips was appointed to this position in 1875, and helped to bring about growth in this area. In 1911, the department of chemistry was converted into a school of chemistry with its own dean. Important contributions were being made even during this early time, such as professor Charles Glen King's identifying the structure of Vitamin C in 1932. The Department of Chemistry, having grown steadily since World War II, was the largest department in the University by 1962.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection related to the Chemistry Department at the University of Pittsburgh was created in part through an initiative to advertise and explain the department through an online website (no longer in existence), and includes academic, administrative, research-based, and publicity information.
Arrangement
These records, documenting the department from the early twentieth century to the year 2000, are divided into seven series:
Series I. Administrative Activities, 1925-2000
Series II. Faculty Information
Series III. Students
Series IV. Academics
Series V. Publicity and Program Information
Series VI. Buildings
Series VII. Photographs
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by the Chemistry Department, University of Pittsburgh in 2005.
Previous Citation
Chemistry Department, Office Files, University of Pittsburgh, 1902-2000, UA.90.08.08, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Pittsburgh (Pa.); University of Pittsburgh; Chemistry -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; University of Pittsburgh
- Administrative Activities, 1925-2000; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series includes faculty meeting minutes, annual reports, grant information, and alumni newsletters.
  - Annual Reports, 1929-1962 (Box 1, Folder 01-14)
  - Department Head Minutes, 1953-1967 (Box 1, Folder 15-18)
  - Faculty Minutes, 1925-1931 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
  - Faculty Minutes, 1935-1942 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Faculty Minutes, 1955-1980 (Box 1, Folder 23-31)
  - Faculty Minutes, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Alumni Newsletters, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Alumni Newsletters, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Alumni Newsletters, 1958-1974 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Alumni Newsletters, 1994-2014 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - National Science Foundation Proposal, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - National Science Foundation Funding (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Space Requirements Program, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Faculty Information, II.
  This series includes lists of faculty members over a series of years as well as detailed information on individual professors, especially during the formative years of the department. It also includes some publications produced by the faculty. These materials include articles, photographs, banquet programs, publications and correspondence.
  - Faculty Information, December 1969 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Chemistry Faculty Lists (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Individual Faculty Members, Alphabetically, undated (Box 1, Folder 42-44)
  - Individual Faculty Members, Alphabetically, undated (Box 2, Folder 01-27)
  - Misc. Faculty Information (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Faculty Publications, 1945-1954 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Students, III.
  This series contains information regarding the student population in the chemistry department and student academic achievements. Records include correspondence, photographs, information about fellowships, articles, and theses of students.
  - Phillips Medalists, Correspondence, 1941-1966 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Phillips Medalist Photographs, 1919-1951 (Box 2, Folder 31-41)
  - Edward Lee Harris (First African-American student to graduate from the chemistry department) (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Fellowships (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Chemistry Alumni information, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 44-47)
  - Thesis and PhD Lists, 1913-2000 (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
  - Chem Major News, 2009-2020 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Academics, IV.
  This series includes notes on lectures given by chemistry professors, as well as information concerning visits from prominent chemists. There is also information about the conduct of academic activities such as the student newsletter, lab safety requirements, honor societies, external conditions affecting study, and testing materials.
  - "Chem Distracts", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Chemistry I Test, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Publications and Lectures, 1925-2017 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Lab Safety (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Chemistry Study and World War II, Article, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Lawrence Bragg Visit, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Lecture, "Synthesis and Uses of Lithium 2, 2, 6, 6 – Tetramethylpiperidide", undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Lectures by Robert Levine, undated (Box 2, Folder 57-60)
  - PLU (chemistry honors society), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 61)
- Publicity and Program Information, V.
  This series contains information developed and collected by the Department of Chemistry to promote and explain the chemistry program offered by the University of Pittsburgh, such as written histories, newspaper articles, photographs, and research information. It also includes the program brochures and publicity fliers that are distributed to educate potential students and others about the chemistry program.
  - Program Info, 1902-1904 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Publicity, 1960-1974 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Department Summary, Histories, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Graduate Brochure Research (Box 2, Folder 65-67)
  - Program Brochures, 1962-1998 (Box 2, Folder 68-74)
- Buildings, VI.
  This series deals with the dedication, construction, and destruction of different chemistry buildings and laboratories. It includes photographs, dedication programs, newspaper articles, etc.
  - Eberly Hall, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Chemistry Library, 1920, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Ashe Auditorium, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Surface Science Center (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Surface Science Center Publicity photographs (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Lab Destruction (Box 2, Folder 80)
- Photographs, VII.
  This series includes photographs created, collected, and used by the Department of Chemistry for inclusion in publicity materials and the advertisement of the department. The photos depict people, places, and chemistry objects, as well as document some important events and visits from eminent intellectuals, such as Albert Einstein.
  - Misc. Unidentified Photos (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Negatives and Slides (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chemistry Faculty Photos (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Professors and Administrators (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ceramics Society (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chemistry Equipment and Buildings (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chemistry Department moving to Alumni, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Recreation (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Interior Alumni Hall, Chemistry Classroom (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - State Hall Laboratory (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pittsburgh/Oakland Scenes (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chemistry Students (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Pittsburgh AAAS Meeting, (Einstein), December 1, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Surface Center Dedication duplicates (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Chem Major News, 1996-2017 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Chemistry Colloquia, 1998-2015 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Assorted Announcements (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Oversize Photographs (Box 4, Folder 1)